I'm going to give you over 10 years of web design knowledge in just 7 minutes.
7분 만에 10년 넘게 쌓아온 웹 디자인 노하우를 모두 알려드리겠습니다.
No fluff, just the good stuff.
군더더기 없이 핵심만 담았습니다.
Are you ready?
준비되셨나요?
Let's go.
그럼 시작하죠.
You can basically boil all the design knowledge that you need to build great websites down to just three things.
멋진 웹사이트를 만드는 데 필요한 디자인 지식은 사실 세 가지로 압축할 수 있습니다.
Layout, color, and typography.
레이아웃, 컬러, 그리고 타이포그래피죠.
Probably heard it said before that people read or engage websites in somewhat of an F pattern.
사람들이 웹사이트를 볼 때 F 패턴으로 읽는다는 말, 들어보셨을 겁니다.
So they start reading at the top left and then they go right, they come back, they go down on the left, they go right, they come back and they go down on the left until they're done.
즉, 왼쪽 상단에서 오른쪽으로, 다시 왼쪽으로 내려오고, 또 오른쪽으로 이동하는 식으로 F 모양을 그리며 시선을 이동한다는 거죠.
But here's the truth.
하지만 진실은 이렇습니다.
That's actually bogus.
사실 그건 근거 없는 이야기예요.
It's outdated information that web designers just kind of keep repeating, and so everybody thinks it's true.
예전 정보가 계속 되풀이되다 보니 모두가 사실로 믿게 된 것뿐입니다.
I might have been one of those web designers, and for that I apologize.
저 역시 그런 디자이너 중 한 명이었을지 모르니, 사과드릴게요.
The truth is, is that people engage with websites and all sorts of different patterns, and forcing them to pay attention in an F pattern might actually cause them to miss important information.
실제로 사람들은 다양한 방식으로 웹사이트를 살펴봅니다. F 패턴만을 강요하면 오히려 중요한 정보를 놓칠 수도 있어요.
So what do you do instead?
그렇다면 대신 어떻게 해야 할까요?
You use something called visual hierarchy.
바로 ‘비주얼 계층(Visual Hierarchy)’을 활용해야 합니다.
Probably seen an image before where there's this big bold line of text that says you're going to read this first, and the smaller line underneath it that says then you'll read it next.
가령 ‘이걸 먼저 읽게 될 거예요’라고 크게 쓰여 있고, 그 밑에 좀 더 작은 글씨로 ‘그다음은 이걸 읽겠죠’라고 적힌 이미지를 본 적 있을 겁니다.
And then this really tiny line that's all the way in the left hand corner that says, and you'll read this last, that is visual hierarchy.
그리고 왼쪽 구석에 아주 작은 글씨로 ‘마지막으로 이걸 읽을 거예요’라고 되어 있다면, 그게 바로 비주얼 계층이에요.
You make the most important elements of a section, the biggest and the boldest.
가장 중요한 요소를 가장 크고 두드러지게 만듭니다.
And then for each other element that isn't maybe as important, you turn down the volume.
덜 중요한 요소들은 ‘음량’을 줄여서 시선을 덜 끌게 하죠.
You make it more inconspicuous for your call to action or buttons.
반면, 콜 투 액션(Call to Action)이나 버튼은 눈에 확 띄어야 합니다.
You want to make sure that they have a high degree of contrast from everything else around them.
주변 요소와 강한 대비를 이루도록 만들어야 해요.
Why?
왜일까요?
Because the main thing we want people to do on a website is click a button.
결국 사용자가 웹사이트에서 해야 할 가장 중요한 행동은 버튼 클릭이니까요.
If it doesn't stand out, it's going to make it harder to do that.
버튼이 눈에 띄지 않으면 클릭도 어려워집니다.
And please, I beg of you, stop using ghost buttons.
제발, ‘고스트 버튼’은 이제 그만 쓰세요.
What are ghost buttons?
고스트 버튼이 뭔가요?
They're buttons that just have an outline without a solid background.
배경색 없이 테두리만 있는 버튼을 말합니다.
The problem is that people don't see them and they don't click on them.
문제는 사용자가 잘 못 보고, 따라서 클릭도 안 한다는 거예요.
For colors, every website should have a color palette that matches the brand of the website owner.
컬러에 관해서는, 모든 웹사이트가 브랜드 아이덴티티에 맞는 고유 팔레트를 가져야 합니다.
Here's a few important things to consider when it comes to color.
컬러를 선택할 때 꼭 고려해야 할 몇 가지가 있어요.
The first thing is accessibility.
첫째는 접근성입니다.
If you pick colors that make it difficult to read text or tough to see elements clearly, it's going to be hard for users to engage.
글자가 잘 안 보일 만큼 대비가 약하거나 요소가 흐릿하게 보이면, 사용자는 제대로 사용할 수 없습니다.
You want to pick colors that have a high enough contrast that even users with visual impairments are still going to be able to see things clearly.
시각적 약점을 가진 사람도 쉽게 볼 수 있도록 충분한 명암 대비가 필요해요.
How do you know if a contrast is high enough?
그 대비가 충분한지는 어떻게 알까요?
Something that I like using is a website calledcoolers.co.
저는 ‘coolors.co’라는 사이트를 자주 씁니다.
You could actually take all of the brand colors from a website and put it into the dashboard.
웹사이트의 모든 브랜드 컬러를 넣어보면
Click on the color contrast teller and it will instantly tell you which colors pass and which super helpful tool.
‘대비 검사(Contrast Checker)’ 기능으로 합격·불합격을 바로 알려줘요. 정말 유용하죠.
Another good rule of thumb for colors is that you want to use a guideline called the 6030 ten rule.
또 다른 팁은 ‘60·30·10 룰’을 활용하는 것입니다.
Basically what this means is that about 60% of your website should use your dominant colors, things like Grays or blacks and whites.
전체 색상의 60%는 주색(보통 회색, 검정, 흰색 등)으로 채우라는 거죠.
30% you should reserve for your brand colors, and then another 10% you want to use something for an accent.
30%는 브랜드 컬러에, 나머지 10%는 포인트 색상에 할당합니다.
So helping things really stand out.
이 10%가 요소를 확실히 돋보이게 해요.
That's a great thing to use for, like your calls to actions or your buttons.
CTA나 버튼에 쓰기 딱 좋습니다.
Is this a hard and fast rule that you absolutely have to use every single time?
물론, 매번 꼭 지켜야 하는 절대 법칙일까요?
No, but it's a good principle to stick with, especially when you're first getting started.
아니지만, 특히 초보자라면 참고하기 좋은 기본 원칙이에요.
Then there's typography.
다음은 타이포그래피입니다.
Typography is one of the most underrated design elements of a website, but it has a massive impact on the readability and user experience.
타이포그래피는 과소평가되기 쉬운 요소지만, 가독성과 사용자 경험에 지대한 영향을 미칩니다.
Thankfully, there's a ton of great options when it comes to fonts.
다행히 폰트 종류는 정말 다양해요.
You've got serifs, you've got sans serifs, you've got handwritten fonts, You've got scripts, you've got display, you've got monospace, and it goes on and on.
세리프, 산세리프, 손글씨체, 스크립트, 디스플레이, 모노스페이스 등 끝도 없죠.
There are three main text elements to consider for your website.
웹사이트에서 신경 써야 할 텍스트 요소는 크게 세 가지입니다.
You've got your H ones or your main headers, and this should be the biggest, most prominent text on the page.
먼저 H1, 즉 메인 헤더입니다. 페이지에서 가장 크고 눈에 띄어야 하죠.
This is going to describe what the entire page is all about.
페이지 전체가 무엇을 말하는지 알려주는 역할을 합니다.
Then you've got your H2 or your subheadings.
다음은 H2, 서브 헤딩입니다.
These act as ways to divvy up the rest of the page and guide a user's attention.
페이지를 구획하고 사용자의 시선을 안내하죠.
Then finally you've got your paragraph text or your P tags.
마지막으로 본문(P 태그)이 있습니다.
You don't want to use really decorative text for this.
본문에는 장식적인 글꼴을 쓰면 안 돼요.
It might look cool, but it kills readability.
보기엔 멋져도 가독성을 해치거든요.
But here's the thing.
그런데 여기서 중요한 점이 있습니다.
Good design without good conversion practices doesn't actually help your clients.
전환율(Conversion)을 고려하지 않은 멋진 디자인은 고객에게 도움이 되지 않습니다.
I designed a website a while back for a client and the result was way better than their old website.
예전에 고객을 위해 사이트를 하나 리디자인했는데, 결과물은 이전보다 훨씬 좋았어요.
It was clean, it was modern, it was chef's kiss.
깔끔하고, 모던하고, 완벽했죠.
The problem was, when we launched it, sales plummeted.
그런데 출시하고 나니 매출이 곤두박질쳤습니다.
Why did that happen?
왜 그랬을까요?
It's because I tried to make it look pretty instead of focusing on good conversion practice.
예뻐 보이게 하는 데만 집중하고, 전환을 고려하지 않았기 때문이에요.
If your design doesn't consider conversion, it's useless to your clients.
디자인이 전환을 고려하지 않으면, 고객에게는 아무 소용이 없습니다.
So what are good conversion practices?
그렇다면 좋은 전환 전략은 뭘까요?
Good conversion is all about reducing friction for users.
좋은 전환은 사용자에게서 마찰을 줄여주는 것입니다.
You want to make it stupid easy for the users to find what they're looking for and to go through and either buy a product or sign up for a service.
사용자가 원하는 정보를 찾고, 상품을 구매하거나 서비스를 신청하는 과정을 ‘말도 안 되게’ 쉽게 만들어야 해요.
And that's done through clarity.
그 핵심은 ‘명확성’입니다.
You want to be crystal clear about who the company is or the person is, who owns the website, and what the user is supposed to do next.
회사나 개인이 누구인지, 그리고 사용자가 다음에 무엇을 해야 하는지 분명히 알려주세요.
Why they should even You also do it through scan ability.
왜 그래야 하는지도요. 또 하나는 ‘스캔 가능성’입니다.
People aren't reading websites, they're scanning through it.
사용자는 글을 ‘정독’하지 않고 ‘훑어봅니다’.
So you need to set things out in such a way that people can bounce around and make decisions.
따라서 이리저리 살펴보며 바로 결정할 수 있도록 배치해야 해요.
And then finally, you want the website to be motivating.
마지막으로, 사이트는 ‘동기를 부여’해야 합니다.
It's not just enough to be pretty.
예쁘기만 해서는 안 돼요.
You actually need to speak to the heart of the user.
사용자의 마음을 움직여야 합니다.
Speak to the thing that's driving them to say yes or no.
그들이 ‘예스’ 혹은 ‘노’라고 말하게 만드는 동기를 건드려야 하죠.
But overall, you want to design for the right audience, not for yourself and not for your client.
결국 디자인은 당신도, 클라이언트도 아닌 ‘올바른 타깃’에게 맞춰야 합니다.
It doesn't matter if you love the design.
디자인이 당신 마음에 드는지는 중요하지 않아요.
It doesn't even matter if your client loves the design.
클라이언트가 마음에 들어 하는지도 중요치 않습니다.
Who does it matter for?
그렇다면 누구에게 중요할까요?
The website visitors.
바로 방문자들입니다.
So do a little research.
그러니 조사를 하세요.
Who's actually using this website.
실제로 이 웹사이트를 누가 사용하는지
Fonts, colors, layout.
폰트, 색상, 레이아웃 등은
Choose them based on the target audience and not personal preference.
개인 취향이 아니라 타깃 사용자에 맞춰 선택하세요.
Finally, make sure that you never stop learning.
그리고 무엇보다, 배움을 멈추지 마세요.
Web designers don't age like fine wine, OK?
웹 디자이너는 와인처럼 숙성되지 않습니다.
We age like a loaf of bread left on the counter.
부엌 카운터 위에 놓인 식빵처럼 빨리 오래돼요.
We go stale unless we keep learning.
계속 배우지 않으면 금세 굳어버립니다.
The web design industry is changing fast, and it's going to continue to do so.
웹 디자인 업계는 빠르게 변하고, 앞으로도 계속 그럴 겁니다.
What worked just five years ago might not work today.
5년 전에는 통했던 것이 오늘은 통하지 않을 수 있어요.
It might not work in the next five years.
앞으로 5년 뒤엔 더더욱 안 통할지도 모릅니다.
And if you don't challenge yourself and stay updated, you're going to fall behind.
스스로를 계속 단련해 최신 정보를 쫓지 않으면 뒤처지게 되죠.
Will AI take all of our jobs?
AI가 우리의 일자리를 모두 빼앗을까요?
Probably not.
아마, 전부는 아닐 겁니다.
But will AI take lazy web designer jobs?
하지만 게으른 웹 디자이너 일자리는 빼앗길까요?
Absolutely.
틀림없이요.
The only way to stay valuable is to keep learning, keep adjusting, and keep leveling up.
가치를 유지하는 유일한 방법은 배우고, 조정하고, 계속 레벨업하는 것입니다.
And you might be asking yourself, that's all well and good, but what do I need to do if I'm getting started today?
‘좋아요, 그런데 지금 막 시작하려는 나는 뭘 하면 되죠?’라는 생각이 드실 텐데요.
Thankfully, I've got another video that I'm going to link to that's going to answer just those questions.
다행히 그런 질문을 해결해 줄 영상을 하나 더 준비했으니 링크로 걸어둘게요.
Make sure that you like this video if it was helpful, and be sure to subscribe so that you don't miss another episode.
영상이 도움이 됐다면 좋아요 눌러주시고, 다음 에피소드를 놓치지 않으려면 구독도 잊지 마세요.
And don't forget, if you don't quit, you win.
그리고 기억하세요. 포기하지 않으면, 결국 이깁니다.